Oscar Serna is speaking in a brand new language.
Oscar: I'm really stressed out!
Oscar is both deaf and blind, or, "DeafBlind."
He works at Gallaudet University, on a project tracking the evolution of a language for those who can’t see or hear.
This new language is called pro-tactile ASL.
The ASL stands for American Sign Language, which uses visual signs for words and phrases.
Pro-tactile ASL communicates entirely through touch.
For example, here’s a sentence in ASL:
Clifton in ASL: I cut down a tree.
Here’s how Oscar would say the same sentence in pro-tactile ASL:
Oscar in PTASL: I cut down a tree.
Historically, DeafBlind people communicated through American Sign Language, Braille, and fingerspelling,
where each letter of each word is signed into a person’s hand.
Hellen Keller, maybe the world’s most famous DeafBlind person, used fingerspelling.
But those are limiting, especially when DeafBlind people want to talk to each other.
Pro-tactile ASL emerged in the early 2000s, as once-isolated DeafBlind people began to form communities.
DeafBlind people have been adapting American Sign Language and adding gestures for things many languages don’t have words for.
For example, this tap on the hand is like nodding.
The language has been evolving ever since.
Clifton: “Now what’s new in pro-tactile is that we’re seeing things that were
used in visual sign language be transitioned from the use of space to the use of the perceiver’s body.”
Traditional theories of language defined it as something seen or heard.
But Pro-tactile ASL proves that language can also be communicated through touch.
And for the people speaking it, it allows for a life with richer communication.
Oscar: "Since I became pro-tactile, all of the channels have opened up; information flows freely."
It’s like going from dial-up to broadband.